hello and welcome to a brand new episode
of smart money on today's episode we do
a deep dive on how you can select the
right health insurance plan what are the
things you need to evaluate before
picking your health insurance and we'll
also help you with an age-wise breakdown
on how much Insurance you need at what
age what are the premiums you need to
pay for it as well joining us in the
show is Girish nyak he's the chief
technology health and officer at ICI
Lombard Girish thanks a lot for joining
us on CNBC tv18 uh well you know I want
to first start with what the importance
of health insurance is in today's
economy because a lot of young people a
lot of people reach out to me saying we
just don't know how to start our
insurance Journey so what is your advice
to them thank you Sonia for having me on
the show and uh like you said it's a
very important uh topic because uh not
many people are really aware of health
insurance uh and it's a very important
aspect of financial planning U health
insurance costs uh the healthcare costs
are rising and the medical costs are
really rising and uh almost every year
we have 63 million Indians who actually
fall below poverty line uh because of
healthcare uh costs and that's a huge
number so uh planning for a financial
emergency is extremely important and
health insurance helps you to do that
now there are many kinds of health
insurance two main kinds are basically
uh the group insurance and the
individual insurance most of us are
familiar with the group insurance
policies which uh you have with your
employer the employer will have a group
insurance policy and uh all the
employees are typically covered by it
there's also the individual insurance
policies where you can take it as a
individual and there are many kinds of
uh individual insurance policies that
you have but I think what is more
important that every individual should
have some sort of health insurance
policy to protect against unforeseen
medical uh emergencies that's very
important I want to talk a little bit
about that right because all of us
employees have a corporate policy uh but
you spoke about the different types of
health insurance there's group health
insurance there is individual health
insurance so for someone who already has
corporate Insurance do you need to take
a top up do you also need an individual
health insurance can you just explain a
little more sure see if Group insurance
policies typically will cover all
employees in a group and uh the cover is
generally around four to 5 lakhs uh per
individual some employees also offer uh
coverage to maybe spouse spouse children
if the employees are very generous
spouse children parents so there are
different kinds of cover that uh
employers provide but most of these
covers are typically around four to 5
lakhs and that really doesn't suffice
for a family uh health insurance uh
cover so it is always advisable to have
an individual insurance cover as well
now normally uh also what happens is
when you are in employment you typically
don't worry about this thing saying that
your kind of employe is going to cover
you and you would be on until retirement
but when you retire say at age of 60 and
suddenly you realize you are without a
cover at that point in time going and
getting cover will be very expensive
unless you had a cover from a
significantly earlier age so that's one
reason why you should get a health
insurance cover even though you have uh
Group Insurance Group cover that is
covering you the other uh other thing is
that uh the uh coverage of the group
insurance policy is typically limited to
what the employer kind of uh decides for
you here you as individual you can kind
of uh have a lot more add-ons that you
want which are more suited to your
requirements and hence uh having an
individual insurance policy is always
better than just having only the group
insurance cover that you normally go
with okay so we talking about the
advantages of personal uh retail
insurance right so individual insurance
basically uh you spoke about how you get
to decide what the cover can be as
opposed to your you know employer
deciding and the other thing is when you
retire you will not just be left without
an insurance so always better to have an
individual not only when you retire say
for example you quit your job quit your
job and want to become an entrepreneur
yes at that point in time again you you
might be wanting to set out on the
exciting Journey but it's better if you
have a individual cover at that point in
time okay so at least the any Healthcare
emergency is covered so when you're
seeing a corporate insurance you have
that you do a top up or you take a
separate individual insurance policy
again there there are multiple options
that you you can take uh a separate
individual insurance policy is always
best because it covers you right from
the base so tomorrow like for example I
said if you go out of the corporate job
and you want to start off on your own
you have a cover right from base but yes
some people from point of view of their
budget would want to take a topup uh
policy so top-ups are much cheaper than
the uh taking a full cover so if you
want to take uh a cover for say 15 lakhs
and your uh employer is giving you uh 3
lakh cover you say take a topup which
will cover you from 3 lakhs to 15 lakhs
so that will be cheaper than taking a
full 15 lakh cover but at the same time
you should realize that when your Group
Insurance stops the first three lakhs
will still be need to be covered by you
so you need that base cover at some
point in time so again it's advisable to
take a individual uh complete insurance
policy and just a topup uh if you can
afford it okay I want to talk about
starting insurance at a younger age
right what are the benefits of buying
health insurance at a younger age and
what age is the right age to
start good question I mean uh it's
always good to start early uh again from
a health insurance point of view uh the
healthier the life the lower the
insurance younger uh customers always
have a uh lower Insurance uh premium and
given our lifestyles today and the kind
of uh stress that is there uh invariably
you see people over 40 45 ending up
having some kind of a lifestyle uh
whether it's hypertension blood the
diabetes India is the diabetes capital
of the world so once you have any of
these when you get into a insurance
policy at that point in time these get
marked off as pre-existing diseases and
your cover the premium is always higher
but if you're already on a policy and
you contract that's there your premium
should would not change because there
you didn't have those uh conditions when
you contracted the policy so it's always
better to get in at early age um when
you start your career start off with
insurance policy okay I want to
understand is health insurance a tax
saving tool or should you look at it
separately well there there is advantage
of tax saving as well because uh uh you
have up to age of 60 years you can cover
yourself and your family and under
Section 80d you get a cover of up to
25,000 of a premium you can uh set off
uh if you're covering a parents uh who
are above 60 then you get additional
50,000 uh set off under the U section
80d so there okay but you shouldn't look
at it as a tax saving tool right that's
an added benefit it's an added benefit
it's added benefit so you when you want
to do your financial calculations it
does help saying that okay this much is
coming back to me as a tax saving but I
would look at it purely as a protection
which you need because one is making
Investments to grow your Capital but
this kind of protection for your capital
in case there is any emergency you don't
draw from your Capital to pay for it so
you have something which takes care of
that uh absolutely absolutely so I do
want to know how much health insurance
Insurance do I need age wise right but
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
take a short commercial break don't go
anywhere when we come back we'll tell
you how to plan your health insurance to
secure your future in just a
[Music]
bit
well on this week's episode of smart
money we talk about how you can pick the
right health insurance and what are the
things that you need to do before you
select your insurance plan uh Girish n n
is with us Girish what are the you know
how is the procedure right how do you
select the right health insurance plan
yeah good question um there are
different kinds of individual uh
insurance plans that are available so
the first basic one which you understand
is the indemnity plan which typically
covers you when uh you hospitalized so
your expenses during hospitalization are
covered by uh the plan there are also
what we call the benefit plans so uh
this kind of gives you a fixed payout uh
if you contract a certain illness like
for example a cancer benefit if you
contract cancer it'll pay out a lumpsum
amount which you take the insurance for
without going into whether you take the
treatment or not that's not uh but in in
the previous case in Indemnity uh you
have to actually get hospitalized and
take the treatment it is reimbursing
your actual costs there's also personal
accident policies which cover uh uh you
against accidents and all so that's uh
the different kinds of health plans you
there the other uh aspect is a good one
uh for typically need a Indemnity plan
definitely okay you definitely need a
indor plans are mostly Indemnity plans
corporate plans are mostly Indemnity
plans uh which cover you for
hospitalization now plans also come with
multiple you as a family uh you can also
purchase a what is called a floater
because uh when you take an individual
plan uh say you take a 10 lakh plan for
an individual then it covers you for a
10 lakh but if you're a family of for
two adults two children you can cover
the entire family on a floater for 10
lakhs then any one of them incurring
expenses of up to 10 lakh is covered the
total uh family incurring expens of up
to 10 lakh is covered so it need not be
an any one of them can incur the expense
it's cover so one year someone can uh
incur the expense other year other one
can multiple people can incur the
expense within the as long as total is
about 10 lakhs okay I have a question
here you earlier said that a corporate
plan U is a lot of generous corporates
sort of include your parents also in the
plan right but what happens when if and
when you leave the job uh to your
parents I mean you can take a separate
plan but largely these individual plans
don't include parents who are above the
age of 60 so what happens then how do
you uh safeguard that so you have senior
citizens plans also okay so a lot of uh
insurers have uh plans for which cover
senior citizens of course the premium is
a bit higher out there uh naturally but
uh that's something that is avilable
okay so uh you can use a senior citizen
plan to cover uh parents again like I
said there's also a tax angle to it
because you cover your parents and uh up
to 50,000 of Premium you can set off in
your taxes taxes okay and how do I
settle my insurance claims that is you
know because there's cash list there is
reimbursement uh a lot of corporates
have cashless uh Insurance processes as
well uh but what is the process like so
typically uh the cashless process works
for both corporate as well as individual
uh insurance claims so if the typically
if the hospital is within the insurer's
network then you can go to the hospital
and uh there'll be a TPA desk out there
where you give your papers and the uh
cashless approval is given by the
insurer and based on that the hospital
treats you without you having to pay out
any uh some of some from your pocket but
if that is not available you can also go
into reimbursement which is basically
you make the payment and then give the
bills to your insurer to reimburse you
for the cost your in card uh cashless is
always better because you don't have to
Shell out anything from your pocket and
this and uh some insur I me we we are
definitely offering a anywhere cashless
facility which is basically even if the
hospital is not within our Network so
our network is about 7,500 hospitals but
uh even if the hospital is not within
our network if you intimate us 48 hours
prior to your hospitalization then we
can arrange a cash Less in that hospital
as well okay so that's a that's a great
benefit to uh to be associated with a
bigger brand like IC LOM got it at
industry level now we are having this
initiative where everyone is trying to
move to a cash lless anywhere that
should be out soon but we we already had
have had it for uh almost a year now so
you don't have that stress of you know
oh there's only a certain amount of
hospitals in your list where you have to
sort of you know go and get your
treatment or else you won't get cashless
so all that is going to be uh sorted out
yeah once we have this uh cashless
anywhere cashless anywhere okay I want
to understand different scenarios right
just real life examples if I'm a 25y old
if I'm a 33 year old I'm a 40y old what
is the kind of insurance that I need so
let's start with the age of 25 in that
age group uh how much Insurance do I
need how much cover do I need
yeah we have a yeah typically uh uh 25y
old I'm assuming single uh just started
off on the job uh would 7 and half lakh
uh insurance would be good enough of
course there are tax benefits which and
that's uh 10,000 would be the
approximate premium including taxes uh
which one would have to pay so uh this 7
and a half lakhs you're saying is uh lar
corporate insurance has about 5 lakhs so
you're saying if someone is 25 and has a
5 LH corporate insurance you have to
take an additional insurance or some
short of better take insurance from uh
the beginning and what happens if you
don't claim the insurance then uh you
get uh bonus which is called additional
sum insured which gets added to the uh
cover some covered every year and
depending on the insurer this could go
up to uh 50 or 100% of the sum insurance
so if you're getting covered by
corporate insurance and you're not
claiming on this uh Insurance soon this
will with the additional summon insure
this could go up to to 15 lakhs on its
own okay because of the additional sum
insured okay now let's move on to
someone who's say 33 years old has maybe
just got married or is planning to have
a child right what is the kind and as a
corporate employee what is the kind of
insurance that they need yeah say that
they would need to up their cover a bit
uh make it about uh 10 lakhs and uh
would have a floater policy covering
both self and spouse so that would be uh
better and of course you have add-ons
because your requirements would have
increased you would have a maternity
benefit which would be uh important
again uh newborn baby cover OPD some PL
offer OPD not all insures offer OPD
because most of the individual insurance
is uh in patient treatment that is you
need to get hospitalized but there are
plans and like we do have plans which
offer uh outpatient treatment which is
basically your consultation your
Diagnostics your Pharmacy charges so uh
you can buy OPD add-on which covers all
these uh benefits so that is something
that uh they could cover on this okay
let's move on to the age group of say 45
to 60 right uh what is the kind of
insurance that they need and since
that's an age which is a tricky slightly
tricky one uh okay we have your 45-year
old businesswoman who's married um
that's a tricky one because that's
really the age when you start developing
some health issues as well so how do you
plan it so like I said plan from before
but at this point in time you typically
say have uh couple of kids so two adults
two kids uh 25 lakh policy uh again uh
is 25 laks enough these
days I'm just giving you a base you can
always there are policies which now
offer 501 CR yeah we have now launched
uh unlimited coverage so oh really I
didn't know that okay you just launched
it okay what does that include it it's
all your everything but without a limit
for coverage okay so and so there's an
extra premium for that perhaps the
premium is uh higher obviously but uh
for again for those who can afford they
can buy that coverage and it covers you
worldwide as well okay so any cost
incurred when you travel anywhere again
like I said for this uh profile You'
also need uh annual Health checkups so
if your plan offers you annual Health
checkups that should get covered because
at the age of 45 you start doing your
health your health checkups more
regularly than when you are 25 right
know I know I understand uh so what
about retirement right there are some
people who have hit the age of 60
suddenly developing a lot of health
issues but have no insurance so what do
they do we have here a 59y old pensioner
has pre-existing medical conditions
perhaps diabetes some even have critical
illnesses like cancer Etc so what do
they do if they don't have insurance
yeah so typically it's very difficult if
you have developed a critical illness
like cancer to get a policy okay um
because that is is a what you call a
non- insurable risk uh as but if you
have diabetes if you have hypertension
there are policies that you can get the
premium will be higher and again as a
good practice again it's always better
to declare your pre-existing illness to
the insurer before taking the policy
okay that's a i a lot of people uh
undergo stress at time of claims because
they have not declared or they have
forgotten to uh mention any pre-existing
illness and diabetes and hypertension
are the most common ones that fall into
this category someone doesn't mention
that uh he or she has had diabetes when
uh getting or has hypertension and
getting the policy when it gets found
out during a claim the claim gets
rejected and you have these other issues
that turn up so it's always better to
declare upfront uh because there'll be
some loading on the premium but you'll
get the policy so for uh a uh person
who's retired without a policy you would
require a cover which typically again
has annual checkups you would add the
Outpatient Treatment op because there
would be lot of um at that age you
necessarily need to see the doctor much
more often than you see at a younger age
so that's a kind of policy you would
take with about 15 lakh cover at least
and a floater again for self and spouse
and that would be in the range of about
say 50,000 okay okay one final question
then um a lot of people get sold ulips
right so I mean I know it's a very Ticky
topic but just demystify it for us
should people go for your lips or not
see I I am strictly against it because I
believe that your investment should be
absolutely separate from your insurance
perfect that's the right way to look at
it and that's a life insurance uh link
policy of course of course health is
health is separate health is sold
without uh yeah without an investment
angle to it without it's protection for
your investment I mean that's how you
look at it but for life insurance for
term insurance say for example you think
it needs to be a separate policy all
together term is I mean you should take
a Term Policy as well because that is
important but take a Term Policy it's
simple Insurance that's uh that's that's
so no to you lips again investment and
protection should be separate okay
that's what you believe that's again uh
to make it more simple that that would
be a but Health we don't have that uh
it's it's purely protection uh look at
it as protection for your Investments
and for your health yeah okay all right
gir thanks a lot for joining in
appreciate you taking the time out and
speaking to see NBC TV8 with that it's a
wrap on Smart money thanks a lot for
watching
[Music]